[Music]
there we are
oh there that beard is growing you guys
have a beard
thing that caught competition going i
mean you both have such impressive
beards
and you're both such impressive
philosophers at the same time
and uh i i feel like uh compared
to you in terms of beards and
well there are there are two genders
they're called beards and women
all right exactly yeah
meanwhile cattle how are you doing oh
yeah very well i'm very well excited for
this talk
ready ready ready to duel get your sword
out
yeah what have you what have you been up
to recently
i've been doing um actually some work as
a psychedelic psychotherapist
oh dear there we go there we go yeah
okay
yeah we just launched a major product in
sweden publicly today called the osmond
foundation
uh where we're gonna uh create
medication out of
silos eben with the karolinska institute
backing it up and
and uh some major philanthropists it's
it's a major break in sweden nation it
was large today
fantastic great to hear it yeah it's all
happening it's all happening great
medicine
yes exactly that's what we think too
so alexander do you remember like your
original you know inspiration for it for
you know you you woke up in the middle
of the night in prague and said oh we
should all have a talk about
uh the archetype replacing the theory of
the subject
in western existential philosophy i'm
quoting your your email here
okay well it it's more like in my
current work i'm working with youngster
the case that actually gonna write
together in tuscany from tomorrow on
with face masks as soon as we leave the
house
but uh what i'm interested in is the
fact that
the sort of the platonist forms i think
disappeared with kant
and and this is different between
content hegel they're not necessarily
with hegel any longer
and that's why ironically hegel opens up
for jung
because what actually comes along after
fraud with jung
is the understanding that the archetypes
that are shaped
in a sort in a more darwinian
evolutionary way
over long periods of time so they're not
perfect forms or anything that we should
aspire to
rather the archetypes are you know
survival mechanisms for the tribe as a
whole or the society as we call it these
days
and uh within the celsius over 60 or 70
000 or even 100 000 years these
archetypes were developed
and with the archetypes we get these
different models including our
personality types within the tribe
that that are optimal for the survival
of the society
and i would say that what young
discovers is that these archetypes
deep inside of ourselves are the things
that we inherit that come
come with the genetic makeup of what it
means to be human the social
biologically developed
and they are actually the forms rather
than the platoonist forms
so so when we talk about today we do
archetypology we try to for example in
men's work
we try to map what kind of men are there
starting with the priest and the king
being totally different and all that
what kind of men are there what kind of
archetypes can we live up to
and aspire to be then this is what we're
talking about we're talking about
personality types actually that serve
the community as a whole
okay can i frame this a little before
before we hear from cattle a bit
yeah so so you know in some of our
discussions we were
we're talking about the difference
between freud and jung a little bit
so i think that's relevant in our
discussions and you guys are both sort
of major freudians you've both read
freud in a lot of depth and
and and i'm i'm perhaps have more
experience with young and reading young
and his followers
so i'd like to be educated on freud a
little bit here in this conversation and
uh
and i'd like a comparison between freud
and young and i'd also
i'd also like to know the difference
between archetypes
and um and platonic forms right
what is the difference and and and also
how does this square with this
jung's idea of individuation and and and
all that
okay is that a good one a lot of issues
yeah
the conversation here cattle do you want
to get in first and then i can pass
and then i can answer to andre's
questions
sure um i think
i mean both just to bring it both you
and i are social analysts that's what i
describe it we're doing psych analysis
but we imply it on society as a whole
would you agree on that um well i feel
like
my i feel like the method for
socio-analysis
however we call it or however it um
emerges
um is emerging um i don't think we have
the the freud of of socio-analysis i
think it's precisely on the level of
method
where that will occur like i always say
you know when it comes to people like
hegel and freud for myself
the reason why i rely on these figures
is not
necessarily because of what they say but
more so
because of the method they develop hegel
develops dialectical method
and freud develops free association as
method
now because of that that is a useful
analytic tool these are useful tools
once you understand the tool of
dialectic once you understand the tool
of free association
you are then free to basically
you could in principle forget about
hegel and freud and
just use the method it's very useful um
and in that sense i think that the
method of socioanalysis is yet to be
discovered
but um it's an extremely exciting
possibility and something that i think a
lot about
i agree completely and i think this
opens the key to anthropology and
anthropology is so big these days uh
because anthropology had a golden age
secretly so in the 20th century was
developed
in parallel with the world of philosophy
and uh
anthropology came out of the union
revolution so out of the junior
revolution we get the archetypes we get
anthropology
and we get to understand the major
narratives of humanity
of course i work with these narratives
all the time i try to find the narrative
there's nothing timeless to anything i
do but the sort of long-lasting
narratives that
constantly return are the ones that we
got used and we were known mitological
and we lived in this ocean for 60 or 70
000 years our genes were shaped and then
we have some other narratives that
actually are very short-lived you only
had very recently
and they're probably basically
paradigmatic they're not here to stay
for very long and that's exactly why the
anthropological revolution also
we should emphasize that it's not just
about hegel or freud but actually the
anthropological religion to me also
points toward a golden age
and this golden age we could call that
social analysis i i would agree with
that completely
it isn't done yet i think shishik for
example has started that process and i
think we're sons of shishek
in that sense what's the difference
between socio-analysis
and what you call tribal mapping you
know because
you know i've talked with alexander for
we have about 60 hours of podcasts and
i'm familiar with
your vocabulary alexander okay okay the
the difference between
psychology and sociology is the same
here so psychology attempts to be a
science if you could ever do
human sciences at all i'm skeptical but
it's psychology greg henrique is not the
guys trying to do that
you've got social psychology between
then you get sociology they attempt to
be human sciences
the great thing with psych analysis is
that it honestly never tries to become a
science even if freud says that but
that's actually what freud fails in that
department
or it wasn't what he intended i would
say today that after la con we all know
that psych analysis is an art form
it's an art form of the human condition
and that's exactly why the attempt to
not become a sociologist but rather look
at yourself as a social analyst
is that you take the art form which is
philosophical
and as soon as you move from psych
analysis to philosophy like
lavish does for example then you
actually
turn psychonauts into an art form social
analysis is just a needed name
for something that doesn't try to be
human science like sociology you can do
sociological arguments to strengthen the
argument but at the end of the day
social analysis is an art form
to try to understand society as a whole
okay
cattle can you um give a bit your your
socio
analysis you know how how your v you you
view socio analysis and
is that in resonance with what alexander
is saying in terms of it being an art
form and not a science
well i um actually wanted to
precisely affirm what alexander says
about this attempt of psychological
and social sociological sciences um
attempting to uh reduce the subject to a
science i think that this
is a absolute um
uh humiliation um and it's it's
it's it's very infuriating
the the reason why it's so infuriating
is be is
is basically because of the subjective
disposition and style of scientists
it's the level of arrogance it's the
level of
um not being able to basically know
their place
um and know their limits precisely
is that where freud went wrong i'm sorry
to interrupt like is that
alexander kind of mentioned it and
that's what i always kind of thought i
always thought well that's where a jung
pic picked up from freud in a sense
because
because uh jung was not so um insistent
on on the rational and the scientific or
look there are a lot here's the thing
freud was an absolute genius
and there are many way there are many
places where freud is wrong
but and this is so crucial and this is
what all of the
straw men of freud don't understand
is that where freud was wrong
he was always wrong in an extremely
helpful
and an extremely productive way gotcha
he was never he was not he was never
wrong in a way
that misled and this is why lacan put so
much
emphasis on a return to freud and a
faithfulness to the concepts and the
method of freud
because freud is not a place where we go
and strictly identify like i said we can
forget about freud once we understand
the method
in in that ideological sense but
when it comes to making productive
theoretical interventions
there are many places where freud was
just a little bit off
where we can make huge breakthroughs
yeah um and i can go into great detail
with that
well i know gerard also said the same
thing about about freud
he appreciated freud and appreciated his
mistakes as well
because he i guess freud is a
speculative you know uh you know
essayist rather than than a pure
scientist in that sense
the great thing about freud is that he's
an explorer
and he's an explorer um that never
leaves
libidinal territory until he reaches the
death drive and then there's another
bifurcation within psychoanalysis which
is very important to understand and
in the affirmation of the death drive he
makes
a little mistake but again a mistake in
a very helpful way in a very productive
way
um again we can go into all of these
distinctions but
i want to revisit your original question
which was about this
this um position on socioanalysis
for me i'm i'm in a place where i'm
very open to the concepts we develop and
i'm very open to the theory we develop
because i think it's
so deeply in its infancy that i don't
want to be premature with anything
so i don't strictly identify with any of
these concepts like socio-analysis
necessarily i think they're very
interesting and i want to explore them
so it's a playful territory yeah i
should add that
freud actually gave up on the whole
scientific thing because it eventually
became psychiatry
and and if you're going to talk about a
science of the psyche must be psychiatry
so because it tries to deal with the
hormones and the chemicals you got in
your brain and
he hardly tries to do anything else but
that's why psychoanalysis i think
jumping up from that point i think psych
analysis was also freud understood
as an art for more more the older he got
he when he came to america in the 1930s
he got sick of all the ego psychology
the americans were doing he felt
completely misunderstood and he
basically wrote books like moses and
monophysim in the 1930s instead he went
into deep history which again he's an
explorer and it's an explorer of the
mind he's explorer of history and that's
why we love freud
there's one thing can i just one
interjection i remember when freud and
young were coming over in their boat
and they both said this amazing thing or
freud said this amazing thing he said
we're here to bring the plague so so uh
yeah
i love that phrase because it's like
it's like the freudian jungian
revolution is is so
um yeah but they were all so frustrated
like philosophers
are they're frustrated because they knew
they would be misunderstood massively
that's the problem when you go from sort
of
elite expertise which to work very
hard box like i do
explore these ideas and then you know
just the genius of these guys hegel
massively misunderstood
nietzsche massively misunderstood even
marx i mean these guys are massively
misunderstood again and again and again
and
probably they knew that as they got
older and that's what he meant when he
said the plague
but we can we can leave florida i agree
with cattle that the interesting thing
is the method rather than the character
we're not gonna we're not gonna lick
freud's
ass or suck a stick or anything that's
just boring i mean we're not idolizing
the guy
we just know that there are great
methods coming out of these guys and
if anthropology was the 20th century i
coined the term social analysis to say
that that could possibly be the big
thing in the 21st century
because we're now entering an era where
man versus technology
is the most interesting topic of all and
we cannot even
imagine human versus human any longer
without involving technology into that
relationship
that's that's key i think i mean i'm
preparing
the question being asked by the machine
to us in 20 or 30 years time that who
are you
from a machete point of view what would
that be in what way are we different and
the answer to that short is pathos which
machines do not have they cannot crack
jokes and they don't jerk off
so they're obviously not human um and
uh i think that's a good starting point
but uh
i'm currently i'm working with rousseau
i'm working with killing the guy once
and for all and
and and i've discovered that it's
actually who
who we go ruth knows already russell is
already i know i know but it's useful
because
because because i'm gonna kill the
pillar saints and and the boy pharaohs
of history in the new book
i'm gonna kill the celebration of the
axial h
and and to do that rosso is the best
personification of that in the
enlightenment because of the
uh amorphous and and the mu
he cannot even understand gender he
cannot even understand sex he he's
he doesn't understand the phallic gays
and the magical gays
are the two things that are important so
he ends up at being this sort of
solipsistic narcissist
now we've written a lot about that
certificate in the past obviously did
the libidos full of this because
the the problem with contemporary
society is that it's basically ruled by
rosa and lynch mobs and the phallus is
lacking
and um and we want to go deeper into
that in the new book
and and look at all of narrative history
from that perspective
okay hold on hold on cattle you wrote a
book called sex
masculinity and god right and alexander
is is
you know always he's always talking
about the phallus and pathos and this
kind of thing and this is
probably why you know you guys are
interested in freud and and um
there's this there's this taboo around
extreme taboo around all of these
these subjects in the contemporary
society which alexander relates to
to rousseau so i want to hear about i
want to hear about that
from you a little bit if my question's
clear
um can you could you could you could you
i i have some things that i wanted to
say about what what bard was talking
about about
human to human interaction and the
machines and who are you okay go for it
we'll come back to this
uh later your book and stuff later
uh-huh okay yeah
and yeah we can we can we can go we can
go deep into that i just wanted to say
that
this this here's the thing is that
in science they call it the mind-body
problem since the origin of science but
what it forgets is that it's body other
and other is always our knowledge is
intersubjective
and science has a huge trouble with
knowledge which is intersubjective
science has a huge problem with the fact
that our knowledge is constitutively
grounded
in inter-subjective relations and we're
trying to figure out
uh what we are and we're trying to
figure out our desire
through the other um and
in that sense to me when bard says you
know
the machine isn't human because they
don't jerk off and they don't have
pathos
what i would say is that the location of
pathos and the location of our most
intimate fantasies
is actually where we connect to
something alien something that
is transforming us into something
totally other
and i think the deeper you go into your
pathos the deeper
the deeper you go into a dimension of
yourself which
is so horrific to normative morality and
which is so
horrific to the normal things that
people accept
among others that you transform the very
nature of your style and your persona
and the reason why science has such a
huge trouble
understanding this dimension is because
science
is because it doesn't understand the
dimension of others is
extremely biased towards what i would
call autistic subjects
and autistic subjects are much different
than the type of subject
which psychoanalysis is concerned with
which is neurotic subjects hysterical
subjects perverted subjects psychotic
subjects
now psychoanalysis i think and a new
book just came out talking about it
should start to approach the reality of
autistic subjects
psychoanalysis should have a theory of
if only so that we can deal with the
problem of scientific knowledge
being fundamentally autistic okay
awesome yeah
and i think autism is is really related
to neurosis more than hysteria because
hysteria is more
to do with emotions right and autism is
a sort of
um well we kind of sort of a hyper
mental state where you're just
disconnected from from
all these things that you're talking
about yeah
i mean they're they're i think there is
a meaningful distinction to be made
between autism and neurosis i don't
necessarily think
that the same thing but i think that
they can definitely overlap
um but the important thing i want to say
is that
um when it comes to the concern the deep
concern
of neurotics and uh hysterics
it has to do with the domain of others
and
and this is why there's a type of off
it's this is why
psychoanalysis disrupts and upsets the
scientific
universe and why science has trouble
sublating psychoanalysis it basically
cannot sublate psychoanalysis
so it says that it's irrelevant
pseudoscience
lacan actually has a good formula for
what psychoanalysis is
which is that psychoanalysis is a form
of knowledge which is still emergent
and which is concerned with the status
of the subject in itself
and which required a scientific universe
to emerge
so in other words science is a
precondition for psychoanalysis but is
not reducing
psychoanalysis that's good i agree here
and this is why we do the studies on
roseau here because
starting with russo if you're looking at
sort of mass culture
early 21st century and the the rampant
hyper narcissism we have today because
of the internet
this goes back to the sauna you cannot
trust the stranger at all
although you desire him all the time so
you you want the gates of the other
this is amu in in in rosso and the
opposite does
which is supposed to be your self-love i
would say that you can't even speak
about self-love i just have loving
relationships with other people
because you're a tribal creature right
this is rosso's weird fantasy
and i think the key here is that he
doesn't
make a difference between the
neuromythology and the eventology
involved
we've been talking a lot about this
before in previous podcasts so so
normatology is basically the eternal
return of the same
but it's also the unconditional love
that we associate with the female body
and with the material love the match our
matriarchal gaze that meets us when
we're born
the other one is the phallic case this
is supposed to be the gates of the
father
the figure or the priest or or the
chieftain or king if you like
who would see you one day and and then
discover you and help you on your way
towards your archetype
now what's what's so misunderstood that
is that
the phallic case it's what so i get go
deeper deeper into it but
the valid case is both nomadological
it's both unconditional
but it's also conditional this sense
that it looks a reality first before it
looks at you
and this is key to psych analysis this
is the really
great psych analyst he has to follow the
case in the sense that
he can look at you but he doesn't
actually have any feelings towards you
he forced you to look at yourself
but he will give you your proper reality
check on every level you go through
during psych analysis and to do social
analysis to do the same thing with
society as a whole
so the phallic case if you get access to
it has an unconditional loving quality
to it if it's fatherly
a mentor or a father who wants to guide
you through life yes
but it first looks a reality before it
gives you the tough news and where you
need to go to succeed
so it's grown up and it's adult and this
is what is so desperately lacking in our
society
it's not only phallus it's the phallic
gaze itself and that starts with the
result because it's i'm a pope it's just
that
trying to get recognition from others
and i think this trying to recognition
from others is a mistake because it
really should be they try to get the
recognition of the elders
or of the fatherly figures or the people
who will guide you through your life
so that you can then go back and explore
self-love
this is completely lacking your also
that's why rosso
is the starting point of the
contemporary mass problem with hyper
narcissism
so you go online today and everybody has
been promised they're going to be
discovered they're going to be seen by
the valid case
there are satellites in the sky that are
looking down on the planet
and you're going to get thousands of
likes for anything you do and now you
discover
20 years into the internet revolution
that nobody likes anything you do
because you're just you're you're just a
mediocre regular human being
and people are devastated by it this is
why beyonce speaks about
depression as the response to the
previous deformation
and be before that that was the
discipline that was the decapitation the
decapitation
during feudalism was replaced by the
deformation during industrialism
and now in the network society we're
moving towards depression itself
and and i think all these things
together when you mix them together you
can do proper social analysis with it
can you make a link to we had this
discussion about cold the cold gaze and
like like
the cold and hot right um because the
phallic gaze i guess is is is
called is a cold it's it's it's both no
no but he does have this
this warmth no no no no this is why it's
so
important to be hegelian because people
constantly put these things as opposites
against
one another they say the mother should
represent certain things and then the
father should represent the opposite
this is just sloppy no what hegel
teaches us is that
very often one thing is one thing to say
we
associate the female body with the
nominology and nomadology dominated our
worldview for hundreds of thousands even
millions of years
the eternal return are the same the
possibility
that an event can happen is only
a four thousand year old idea and if the
event happens
things can be changed forever so a new
technology can come along or a savior
can enter the scene and suddenly
everything changes
and then history has changed ever
forever after that point in time
now if the event the evantology comes
with us only four thousand years old
it's not the opposite of nominology
numerology is still there the world
undeniably circulates
it adds to it so the phallic case must
be understood
as a case that is both normal logical
which is warm
and eventual which is cold yeah
well i was thinking a hard trick i was
thinking is so important
i was thinking in alchemical terms
because the the you know
uh the sulfur is the heat that rises and
mercury
is the coolness that that comes down but
actually they're
they're one thing they're not they're
not separate so
yeah but this is a dynamic relationship
between them and
and um well the hegelian i would say
very often
says that one thing is one thing only
and the other thing you start talking
about eventually
is that thing plus something else and
it's the plus you add to it that's
interesting what i love with cattle's
work and would love to get into tonight
though is the fact that cattle is pretty
much obsessed with negative dialectics
and negations
and they also play into this so it's
uh hey it's wonderful to be diagnosed
with your go go for it uh okay what
you're saying here hey golfing says one
thing is one thing
it's crucial that it's one thing plus
lack
you know so usually what the opposing
it's usually what the opposing poll
is the so-called opposing poll is
usually
empty and lacking and there's a lot
of of responsibility actually on the
higher poll or the one thing that's
actually one thing
to go into what its own lack is
because when it goes into what its own
lack is it actually
gains that third weird power of
transforming itself into something
really different
so in that sense i mean it's a it's a
really use again it's a really useful
tool to analyze
oppositional determination because
usually when you have opposites
usually it's one thing like for example
like
uh marx would say for example the
two-party state
is actually just an effect of capitalist
reproduction and it's just reproducing
capital
and then the two-party system is kind of
a lack it's empty
and we all know it's empty and now we
see it's empty because it's just a
reality tv show
yeah um yeah so you could you could
certainly apply that on demandology
normatology normatology of the
relationship too and the great thing
with hegel is you shouldn't think too
chronologically about him
the thing is that if you study something
you're free actually to change the order
of things
when you study it because here for
example evan if evantology is both
hepatology genomicology at the same time
nomidology is the one that has the
negation it lacks scientology
so fair like the thing is what bard's
saying here is that
if if you are like
a pure you know if you're the
singularity of the of the subject
you can actually rewrite history like
and
i mean even bard does that as an active
performance like
you know emphasizing certain uh
chronological dates which he's
organizing that past
you know that's as something that
emerges with bard as a figure and that's
what a great thinker
in some sense does is creates his own
history
yeah the future is contingent but the
past is necessary
the thing that got me excited about
hegel a little bit
um was was was when i connected it to
this idea of buddhist emptiness um
and then and then and then cattle was
saying oh you can't reduce it to
buddhism
um but i think there's something radical
in in that and
buddhist emptiness that that that is
there's an actual practice
you know thing that you embody and stuff
whereas if i just read hegel it would be
just propositional to me and
you know interesting to apply in an
intellectual way but how do you apply
that like like
in terms of you know a practice that
would transform you and change you and
and yeah well that's what i'm interested
in so let me give the distinction i give
and i'm not saying that i
i mean i have actually you know explored
buddhism i've gone to buddhist temples
and talked to buddhist monks and so
forth
i'm not i do not call myself an expert
on buddhism
but um when it comes to
the difference between um what i would
call
um popular western buddhism and
this is i'm not saying this is like if i
talk to the most
rigorous deepest buddhist monk i'm going
to get this but when i see the popular
western buddhist philosophy um
it's it's it's an it's a and what i see
is a
basically an a historical emptiness and
now the emphasis now that now here's the
here's my my
distinction i'd want to make is that
buddhism emphasizes
the inner void you know even if you go
to the
the buddhist sutras they emphasize the
the heart and they emphasize the the
empty fullness of the heart um and they
place
that as a sort of uh uh an
anti you could say an
anti-transcendental principle
in some sense um and i think and i think
so you get to the the
the vagina which which it is it changes
that
that and i think you're talking about
mahayana right now yeah this is
incredible and this is and this is
this is not nonsense this is incredibly
deep stuff
what i'm what i'm what i'm trying to say
emerges in
hegel and also i think emerges in
figures like heidegger
is a type of historicity of nothingness
so
the focus is not so much on the
empty void of the subject but more so
the way in which subjects
organize around the void and i think
that
so the emphasis would be for example on
the way buddhist communities
organize their practices their rituals
around the void
and that's so interesting to think
because to me
it gets me into thinking metaphors of
black hole it gets me into thinking
metaphors of
subjectivity as the sort of the
s or language as the material signifiers
which are organizing around
a void or organizing around a black hole
and i think we get
the potential to develop a deep
historical theory
of what the becoming of this void
entails
um and i think that in that sense what
i'm saying is
i'm less interested on the absolute
ontological validity of
what buddhism identifies but more so i'm
interested in
the collective socio-cultural practices
which are developed
around cultivating knowledge of this
void
i i would add that i think that we i
think i would just say i think that we
get that capacity and hegel let me just
say
that because for hegel the ultimate
negativity and the ultimate void
is confrontation with death itself
and the ultimate fear in the heart of
the subject
that basically hegel says you are
brought to your truth and you discover
your truth in the face of death itself
the night of the world a subjectivity
yeah
yeah i agree when it come to buddhism
though there's a difference in mahayana
and
variana and to me mahayana perfects
numerology takes nominology to logical
conclusion
which is that the only way for something
that endlessly repeats itself is to try
to get out of the loop
okay and then of course that's what
mahayana buddhism tries to do
but the varying response is it's mixed
with zoroastrianism especially it comes
out of tibet and central asia
it adds the eventological element so it
puts buddhism
into a much more social category and the
social category can be other things too
now the interesting thing though is that
none of these traditions talks about
individual subjectivities
anything else but a void to be filled
because it's essentially along the
timeline
you're a child hey you're nobody you
haven't lived a life at all
so in zoroastrianism for example the
goal in life is to live a full rich life
called horvathot
then also to die one day with harvard
thought if you're lucky
to pass on transcendence to the next
generation which is called the meditate
this is exactly why the person's never
built pyramids for example this is
exactly why they
just threw the corpses out of the desert
where people died because you already
had achieved what you set out to do
which was to live a full life however
thought to then pass
all the heritage to the next generation
so to be full as a subject is to have
lived a full life
that's the idea there that's not too
different from the gaelian concept
because the subject is constantly
trying to fill itself with content and
obviously in lacont it goes all the way
and la convey success it's impossible it
will never happen
we desire to fill ourselves with some
kind of content and it's still the
gaping hole that it always
was and yeah because if it wasn't we'd
go and kill ourselves
so rasters would agree but the serastius
would then put that
into the perspective you're a child here
you can an adolescent here that you're
an adult here
you can then become an elder you can
become a foreign father even if you're
really successful at things and you know
be a role model
you can become an icon after you die
even you can become a smaller god
all of these things are possible within
that time span because they look at it
tribally
and they look at it over the entire
lifespan i think that's a valeriana
buddhism catches on that's what it does
well the thing that i would i've i'm
sort of obsessed with and
it's very fluid it's not you know so
just forgive me here uh is is i there's
this
bard's eventology which you know which i
guess begins in zoroastrian and moves on
with judaism and
and so i want to combine i want to
combine vagina with
with uh with the hebrew tradition which
has a story to it it has a kind of a
it has this narrative structure as well
so i want to combine the narrative
with the deep non-dual um with the deep
non-dual traditions on some
level uh i don't know if that's possible
but those are two my two obsessions
uh yeah i i can speak to that so
there's an important i mean i would
recommend first to
read the um the intro chapter to less
than nothing epper c muave
um where i think he gives the a clear
precise formula of the hegelian
dialectic as basically
the becoming of narrativization itself
so the becoming of narrativization
itself is the story
self-consciousness or subjectivity is
telling itself about being itself and
that
is the becoming of the subject so it it
it basically
it basically mobilizes it's basically
the ultimate mobilization of narrative
the ultimate movement of narrative
that's what we're studying and
that is a story which is emerging
it's emerging in our collective story
it's what we're doing right now
like the emergence of all these podcasts
the emergence of all these
you know talking about deep
philosophical concepts this would be
something that hegel would have
anticipated as kind of the the um the
emergence of a more distributed
philosophy which is
again working out the concept itself
i agree strongly i mean that's that's
why i'm talking about process and event
so uh at the end of the day
process was the original philosophy we
we we
mistakenly think that things started
with plato or something and in the west
and then people came along and did
process later no heraclitus was long
before played on before half of this we
had the saurons
and actually if you read beyonce
rewriting of east asian history which is
fantastic
you discover that all east asian
cultures have always emphasized the
symmetries and constant process and
movement and this idea that there are
fixed forms or anything like that
that just comes way way later with the
greeks especially with plato and it's
actually quite isolated to the west it
doesn't make much sense to the nation at
all
the indians never subscribe because we
started off talking about archetypes oh
they are
the archetypes universal you'll find
them everywhere don't worry about that
archetypality will be very universal
because anything that was developed over
hundreds of thousands of years
was probably developed both with inuits
in canada and with people in new guinea
and in brazil in the jungle
you will find it because people were
nomads and people people were nomadic
that's why we call it no mythology
nomidology is both it's the less it's
adolescent term nominologies both that
were on the move all the time so the
story is about
how we have to be on the move all the
time where otherwise we die but you know
methodology is also it's a storyal
process
so it becomes quite natural no modality
becomes the eternal return of the same
every season you come back to the same
point every year is a new year but it's
still the same year as the last year and
with the permanent cell we discovered
that if we store information the way we
store grain
then we the way we in you know we build
huge constructions we irrigate water
all these things we do create abundance
on a level we've never seen before
and that creates the possibility of a
different world the previous one
for better or worse yeah but eventology
means that i hope this could be a better
world than the previous one
that idea is then brand new it's not
opposed to nominology it can be added to
nominology
this is what the chinese and the indians
try to do as well of course and the
problem was with the abrahamic religions
in the west
especially islamic christianity is that
they threw out
the nominology stay with evantology and
the massive focus on what muhammad or
christ did in certain dates and
what they sacrificed and you know the
battles they want or whatever
this is obsession with these guys which
eventually leads to the separation of
church and state of the west becomes
becomes unattainable to keep
evantology outside of numerology and
then no modality becomes capitalism
it came back to hardest it was obvious
that capitalism
as the great ghost of our culture is no
matter logical it's just the repetition
of the same all the time that's what
capital is
and we're not fighting with that it's
called market forces and we
we see the emptiness in an enemy logical
sense in that
we should just accept that it's there
but the eventology has to come back in
again
its name is phallus we threw it out with
the bath water after 1945
and we're lost because of it
post-modernism if you're criticizing is
nothing but nomidology again without
eventology
that's the problem so i want to know
what the
the masculine and the feminine principle
have to do with like the phallus and and
are you know are we
are we is that the same thing or no no
no
maybe you wanted to uh precursors are
always
important that's number one thing with
hegel right the precursor to the event
before the event is even possible is the
fact that men learn
from the context where they are at so to
go out hunting or to win a war you learn
from the
circumstances where you're at but you
also forget that information the next
thing you do because you can't keep it
so the next war is going to be like the
previous war anyway there's no
technological development or anything
like that at all because you don't store
information anywhere
when somebody dies the information dies
with them everything is memorized beside
that
the max amount of information is
constant for hundreds of thousands of
years
before written language arrives and
changes the rules of the games
completely
now with the now that this this is why
event becomes a new idea
but it should always be combined with
nominology we should always have a
society that respects and understands
that
human life is both circular and linear
at the same time
that is what i require this is called
process event then i would add to that
where catalyst work is so damn important
here
is i think cattle gets hegel better than
any of his contemporaries
and i think negation the way hegel
percent is probably the third
idea that philosophy ever came up with i
think anything else that philosophy came
up with is
minor compared to process event and
negation
that's how important hegel is can can i
can i go into
well thank you bart for the compliment
um can i can i go into a little bit of
um
uh your question there um andrew about
the masculine and the feminine the
difference between this yeah
i want to go there for sure but what the
hell we're talking about when we say
masculine and feminine
you know it's no it's no everyone knows
you know the famous statement by freud
that
you know the concepts masculine and
feminine are the most confused concepts
in science and
you know the way we use those concepts
are extremely confusing
there are some lacanians who actually
prefer to use the concepts left and
right
geometrical concepts instead of
masculine and feminine they claim that
we move too quickly when we label
something masculine and feminine that we
were usually you know stumbling around
in the dark with these concepts well
alexander uses phallus and matrix as the
two
sort of right so i mean that's
interesting i mean
i don't i mean we could have a
conversation about that so yeah the
the the thing is is that when we when
when freud was going about defining
these things
basically what he means when he says
libido is masculine is that what he
means is that
libido is action and libido is one
so libido is action and libido is one is
probably
more accurate than saying libido is
masculine to be honest
so saying libido is action is a good
starting principle and then you can say
that the opposite of libido is kind it's
again like this
this hegelian principle of there's one
and
a lack and basically the lac
is what we call femininity yeah and
femininity becomes what we
we label it as passive so the classical
uh uh metaphysical distinctions are
active passive and
maybe that doesn't matter precisely but
there is
a way in which what we call masculine
and feminine is kind of an
active pointing going
and wants to wants to go in and
the passive is receiving
being in sure so
this basic distinction about going
in and being in is
what we mean when we say masculine and
feminine
and so you can even say for example
science is masculine
because it's constantly pointing and
trying to understand
the outside world trying to get
somewhere where it could finally
find its place where it could be in yeah
and you could say psychoanalysis is
somehow feminine
because the analyst is a pure receiver
pure pure receiver of the subject's
speech
you can just say anything and this the
analyst will just be there
and it's just receiving you can
come in sure
yeah i call these things phallic and
magical and i'm very adamant about it so
libidos on the phallic side
what we mean with that is that
absolutely yeah what i mean with that is
that nomidology is fundamental
nomidology wins at the end
uh the universe started with a big
bounce anyway so it's it's
it's just in and out in and out okay
pumps right anything that pumps and as a
pulse is normal
so of course men come to women because
women represent reproduction they are
the ones we produce they give birth to
children hey that's half the job done
that's the non-methodological part
eventology then when it arrives four
thousand years ago because of
information accumulation
is that men can start to make themselves
redundant outside of the reproductive
process and that redundancy can be
turned into an abundance of resources
and we call that civilization that's why
men
are usually the ones not women who are
on fire about changing the world for the
better
and what they mean with that is that we
could build things we never built before
we could try to do things we never tried
before
we have the resources now and we could
do that and to give that some kind of
direction is the job of religion so the
job religion is basically
religion is fundamentally a masculine
enterprise not a feminine one
if the guys get the religion right
usually the women benefit from it it's a
very selection take on religion but
actually agree with that
i think religion is not a women and
children thing i think religion should
definitely be a men's thing to begin
with
it should be the separation of priest
and king to begin with to understand the
two different
archetypes and then you can organize the
world accordingly
and this is where the engineer or the
architect comes into the picture why i
celebrate these things in my work with
john certainly is that
these ideas of the engineering the
architect is what we need today you're
going to save the planet we're going to
make people get along through crypto so
they don't kill each other and we're
going to make strangers love each other
through new technologies
all the things that we need to do right
now urgently the next 50 to 100 years
point towards a new eventology a new
massive phallic mission this phallic
mission is basically save the planet for
the huma
for humans to begin with and then
prepare humans for meeting the machine
eventually along the way
now these are huge technological
challenges and technological challenges
are perfect for evantology
that's exactly what eventology tried to
do when it built civilization
over the past 5 000 years and this is in
the masculine in the sense that it's in
the phallic mode
because the the the magical mode is the
reproduction and keeping everything
going so a new generation can be born
without that we're done
the phallic can then add value so that
the next generation could possibly have
a better life than the previous one or
at least dream about it
that's where the phallic dreams come
into the picture look
religion religion is going on what bard
says
religion is what happens when
men of a particular historical time
figure out how to do what's best
and what's in the best interests of the
women and the children
in a way in which it creates
positive some synergies among the
community and that's what we call
religion and
the reason why religion has declined is
because the religions
of the modern period and the pre-modern
period no longer
match the historical reality of the 21st
century
and so that requires new phallus
it requires new thinking about
masculinity in order
basically what what you end up trying to
think is
a new religion and and and that's why i
say
religion is not something
which is subject once we understand that
religion evolves
once we understand that not only does
religion evolve but religion
leads to a type of bootstrapping process
where it causes its own it's its own
cause that that
in that sense when we when we try to
think about what the the future religion
will be it'll
almost be like uh the metaphor of jesus
where you die and you rise from the dead
religion died yeah and now i agree with
that
arise from the dead i think religion is
rising from the dead and i think all the
traditional religions are going to arise
as well but they're going to
transform they'll arise in it they'll
they'll arrive at the time
yeah they'll they'll emerge in a totally
new form yeah i agree
yeah and and this sort of activism and
individualism that the carton content
was so practiced didn't really work that
well do they so we're throwing some old
religions out
with the bath water anyway that we have
developed the last 300 years didn't
really work
didn't didn't have universal appeal for
very good reasons so
so we can at least admit that those are
religions too the bad religions
basically newton descartes
leibniz i would say spinoza
hume kant all of these guys are geniuses
but they fall short in such an important
way
that ultimately changing the axioms of
their philosophy
leads to their destruction i agree
strongly yeah so it's a theological
question to be honest about it i
agree on that completely so yeah that's
what we're heading that's where we're
heading next we need to build that and
and
i would say in my work then this is why
i'm critical of taoism although i love
the daoist tradition
i almost converted to taoism in the
1980s but i refused it yet
the problem with daoism is that it stays
within the end of the youngs it stays
within this idea of masculine feminists
two major forces
of reality and this exactly why chinese
culture has to introduce confucianism as
a third force
and that when china tends to go
tyrannical i would say that the first
division you need to make is the
division between different men within
masculinity
this is different between the for
zoroastrians the difference between the
king and the priest are fundamental
that's the first division you make and
after you made that division which is
the division between mind and body
are both separate entities and also
collaborative entities so you understand
how you function as a human being
after you've done that you could start
saying oh okay by the way men and women
can also be separated
and by the women and men have different
stories or different narratives about
reality and how things work
because the women's the female narrative
or the magical narrative will always be
the story about everything returns to
the same
it could go that's any fair tell you
tell children will be accepted that way
it's also about the nomadic tribe
getting up in the morning and moving on
to the next stop because otherwise they
die
these are normal logical stories and
they're fantastic they're the basic of
narrative
but on top of that you can have the
mythological narratives that are
possible
after since the last four thousand years
which are called civilization
which we need more than ever to talk to
top on the
logical narratives these these this is
the return of the phallus that we're
talking about
and the phallus must be split the
problem with daoism is when i work with
this is like
oh yeah you got the yin yeah that's
numerology and you got the yang and you
think that should be eventology but the
yang is just one thing
what zoras just realized that was you
had to split that so ahura and master
are two different entities within the
masculine
the ora which is ancient persian for
being
and musta which is ancient persian for
sense or mind
are two different entities the
collaborate
means it's both being and its mind at
the same time which is way more hegelian
as you can just find out
yeah that means there's always three
here and this is what judaism inherits
because when judaism rewrites the exodus
out of egypt after the encounter with
the zoroastrians in babylon
and and the the hebrews come back as
deuce to to the promised land and build
the second temple
sponsored by the persians they rewrite
the exodus
it's no longer just moses leading his
people it's moses and his two siblings
moses aaron and miriam and with moses
being the priest and aaron being the
king with the chieftain and with miriam
being the metroid you get the triadic
structure that's the most stable
structure
over time and i would say it's the both
imperial and the national structure of
any system
larger than tribe we ever invented has
to have this sort of tragic structure to
it
the u.s constitution is a perfect
example of that okay but is it it's a
dynamic structure right the the thing
yeah
it's a dynamic structure whereas whereas
a solid structure like exactly in the
ind the indians have it in religion at
least they got it with the shiva and
and kali but the problem with chinese
culture chinese culture does not have
the triad
it has either the yin or yang or it has
the confusion dictatorship or tyranny
more or less
and that the only reason why
confucianism became such a big idea in
china
two thousand five hundred years ago was
because it left
out the three and stayed with the two
so there was no dialectical turn yin and
yang are not the dialectical
relationship
you say try towards a balancing act that
sort of harmony a harmonious act
and that is very similar to the
separation of church and state which is
of course than the problem with the west
these are the two major problems we deal
with not philosophically is the
separation of church of state fifth
century
rome okay major problem for the west and
we live with the consequences ever since
and china has always had the problem the
talisman itself was not
enough and that's why dallas split and
eventually turned into buddhism's mother
and child worship in china
and then the other version was
confucianism and the problem with china
still today
is that china has such a fiendishly hard
problem dealing with
plurality and plurality is the key to
freedom and to creativity
that's what the chinese are dealing with
right now
and i think we we owe them a response to
that we owe them a philosophy as a
response to see you in pink's current
tyranny dictatorship in china
and that has to be uh a son socracy
which is developing but a plural system
and this is why these terms antagony
come back all the g again like
you're only becoming intelligent by
constantly being challenged by opponents
who disagree with you
rather than people who just agree with
you all the time and this is why we
criticize the dictators of history in
the new book
called the boy pharaohs and pillar
saints because they're too scared of
being antagonically challenged in
anything they do
because that's requires a system that is
plural
at its core and china still hasn't
developed that
yeah and i i think of the the freudian
repression when you repress that
antigone then you get
um all this chaos that we see today and
yeah yeah i regret this dynamic you know
uh
um uh conversation or
or or process of under you know rubbing
up against each other which the
masculine
really enjoys right but why is there
then so much
like um
why is there so so much loathing of the
masculine in the culture at the moment
like
that's that's it seems very
present or it's it starts after 1945.
it was hitler and stalin and colonialism
and we blew up the bomb
in august 1945 and scared the out
of ourselves we realized that we can
kill ourselves easily we can press a
button and kill ourselves
now after 1945 that all those things are
phallic i mean
there's nothing more phallic than
dropping an atomic bomb or something
so yeah we're terrified of fellas
because violence can also kill us
so if phallus is associated with shadow
it will kill us
so so we are dealing with false but the
way we dealt with fallows in the west
was that we try to hide it and push it
down and suppress it and take it away
and
jung and you know uh schmidt
all these other guys warned us about
doing it and strauss wonders about doing
it it's now coming back to haunt us
and i think that's exactly what happened
because once the internet came along
and and we got into this sort of very
effeminate victimhood culture
uh that we're stuck with now and we
stuck it for the past 30 years
the only way out of that is some genuine
phallic projects
that could move humanity forward and
that's why i'm writing about
engineers and architects and why i love
them and i want to work with engineers
and architects and everything i do my
philosophy because
i think we need to be whole new
technologists that challenge our minds
and and
we can create a better world because of
it we need cosmopolitanism
we need the love of strangers that's
called crypto we need
uh we need uh to fix ecology we call
that echotopianism because
environmentalism is simply not enough
it's just dystopian
and at the end of the day the ultimate
goal of all this is to create a
protopianism not another utopianism not
another dystopianism we had enough of
both
so it's again it's a dialectic
relationship where we discover that
protopianism is the way forward
and protopianism is the original
sorastian idea of the frasso
an ever renewed refreshed world with new
challenges that we take on gladly every
day
that kind of world is the only way we
could could consider and think of and
that's why the protopians to me
is the name of the digital priesthood
we're building right now
we are the first protopians right here
and we're going to work with artists and
philosophers and
and architects and engineers and all
these people who want to build a new
world
and if we need to make an exodus to do
it we'll make the exodus otherwise
we'll do it right here and now where
we're located we're doing digitally
right now during the corona months we've
done it immensely already
i think augmented reality is the next
big thing over the next 20 years
then probably we'll meet aai we can
collaborate with ai in a symbiotic
transcendental relationship with it
so i'm i'm i think all these things are
possible it's my job to write
about it the way
marx and nietzsche wrote about promising
things like the proletariat or the uber
mansion today that is writing about
protopianism
i just wanna i just wanna say uh maybe
going off a little more and developing
uh your question there um andrew about
why is there so much hatred of the
masculine
um freud knew that
the hatred of the father was actually
what under
what was underlying hatred of the father
was the deepest possible love of the
father
people people hate the father or people
hate the masculine because it's an
unconscious provocation
on masculine energy to
come up with a better solution to our
current problems
um people are people it's it's
it's the way it's the way in which you
know
that the girl or the you know it's a
it's a way in which
that the girl who has a crush on the guy
will
provoke him provoking testimony poke it
poke at him
test him torture him even you know
that he'll become the man she wants but
but she can't go about doing it directly
she has to go about doing it with ira
irrational
indirect provocations and the man has to
you know raise his consciousness to the
level of understanding
what's going on and i think that men by
and large
you know over the past few years and i
think increasingly in the future
are going to rise to this challenge uh
yeah i agree
disconnect from completely and end up
sort of
uh you know disconnected right the
problem though with this test
that's going on
young guys i found out it's a huge
test i say yes it is
the problem though is that if the young
men jump to conclusions too quickly they
will go towards tyranny and they will
love the fake fellas
that's exactly what happened in the
1930s with stalin and hitler and those
guys too
the risk for that is actually immense
especially the united states
so uh i think i think that's what we
wrote about the fake fathers and
authentic fellows in digital libido we
weren't about the fake falls
again there are way more fake phalluses
around at times like this than their
authentic phalluses around
so the question is that who is then the
authentic phallus and could we ever see
him
and you and i under have explored this
together with thomas hamrick and our
webcast together i would say that the
fake phallus
comes out of the lynch mob and senses
that there's a shared voice within the
linchpin it's like a shared agreement
with a little lynch mod
and to get the tension out of the lynch
mob and find an object and attack the
object the scapegoat
the scapegoat mechanism somebody
personifies the energetic all of a
sudden puts on a uniform and
becomes hitler and it rises to power
very very quickly
i think the risk for that is enormous
it's happened already in china his name
is xian ping it says 2014
is now officially the dictator of
communism maybe we don't want
yeah we don't want that to happen in
other places but but the problem is this
you got to wait for the authentic
phallus you've got to ask all these
fellas
who are you and what were you authentic
and the only authentic fellows
is really the guy who stands up to the
lynch mob and say we can do
better than that we can do better than
being dystopians of vulgar utopians we
can do better by being protopians
instead
and this is what is required for us to
go protopian so the guy
stands up and says no to the lynch mob
he might be crucified because of it
that's happened before
but he is the high project the precursor
is the high project
to what we call the savior in our
culture that the jews call the messiah
the messiah of course
and the persians the persians invented
the concept called it the cell shown
and please note the sultan is a function
it's a function that steps in with the
phallus slackening society
personifies the phallus has the phallic
energy
and gives you the phallic vision and the
phallic strategy and says we're gonna go
there and the name for that is exodus
it's all about the exodus and and i i
believe strongly that we as philosophers
have to formulate
that exodus into digital and into the
global and into the world we're going
into now the paradigm shift that we're
currently going through
and the implicated order of that was
capitalism the explicit order of that is
potentialism to see if we could go
towards a communism of some kind
but we need to do precisely that that's
that's the greatest challenge the next
50 to 100 years in the world of
philosophy according to be
and that is where i tell the guys to
watch out and wait for the authentic
files wait wait wait
because if they go for fake phalluses
now they go for all these alt-right guys
and soon they're going to be old enough
guys around
they try to be the cheap the quick fix
the short route
to tyrannical powers you can finally
submit
to the to that fake father figures you
can finally get all that frustration out
of your system
can i i want to go back just just a
little bit because i think maybe cattle
has some good insight into the the
psychoanalytical
basis of why we have this fake phallus
and why we have the the you know what's
the authentic and what's the fake
phallus if
if you follow bard's um analysis here
right
the fake phallus being the sort of
pseudo-masculine
and i guess the authentic philosophy
being the
the really courageous you know one who
stands up to the lynch mob etc
how does that happen what is the the you
know uh you know i i'm i'm
i'm asking because we had a kind of
conversation and i i always
have this uh you know kind of freudian
jungian idea there's this devouring
mother and the tyrannical father
and and that the and edvard was kind of
coming down on me
about that and so i want to i want to
hear um
i want i want to hear you if you have
insights on on
what is what's going on there
i think i mean
i you know i was having i was having i i
will answer your question
i i was having a a a session i won't
disclose any information other than
an interesting anecdote um
where there was basically a guy
struggling with orientation and desire
you know i don't know how to direct
myself and i don't know my desire
you know and i i basically said to him
you know what does it feel like when you
have an erection
you know you've got your orientation
you've got your desire there's no
question about it
you know your orientation you know your
desire the reason why you don't get your
orientation and desire is because you're
disconnected from your body
you you need to work from the ground up
you need to integrate your dick
you need to integrate your stomach you
need to integrate your heart
you need to integrate your voice you
need to integrate all of that
in order to think properly so that
you'll have your orientation and desire
and for me that would be an authentic
phallus
an authentic phallus is a man whose
action
is aligned with the actual energy of his
body
and a pseudo phallus is a man
who's basically caught in the clouds and
he's using his direction and his
orientation and his desire
to mask the actual sexual conflict of
his body
full contradictions of his body he can
speak his desire
and he knows what he wants and he's no
doubt about that
the man who the man who is
um using his intellectual orientation
and his intellectual desire
to run away from the problems of the
body is for me
the fake phallus and those guys don't
actually have relations
those guys are thrown around by their
wives it doesn't matter how intelligent
they are
you have the intelligent you could have
the most intelligent guy in the world
and just wait to till you see the
dynamics at home with the wife
yeah the woman will throw him around
like he's nothing yeah
and the wife was always controlling him
on some level
because that's what we talk about he's
in control on his mind but he's not at
all in control because he's just
connected with with you know she's
probably frustrated because her
tests are too successful so there you go
he's
the the real that's what we talk about
boy pharaohs
pillar saints and we also discussed
peter pan syndrome the peter pan
syndrome yeah
and peter towson works and we also
developed the idea of the caligula
syndrome that's fantastic because
we call legalization we also have an
understanding that you might be
perfectly fine you just haven't gone
through the cat the last sessions you
haven't discovered actually how you're
gonna define your desire but actually
the world around you is so
crazy and follows so much penis
hatred or whatever
that that you cannot be a man in that
environment you need to move somewhere
else to be a man that's caligula
syndrome as well
all these things peter pan syndrome
caligula syndrome and historically
speaking the problem with the boy
pharaohs and the pillar saints
are essentially think of it as 11 year
olds who
want all the advantages of having the
grown-up man's penis and be a respected
man physically but doesn't want to pay
any of the prices required for that and
not take on any response yeah there's a
price
requirement for a sacrifice to be made
and all that right there
yeah that that soda fallow starts there
that's exactly why these
tyrants that we talk about in our work
the anojects who become personified and
put on a uniform
have this tendency to be like 11 year
old boys who
theatrically perform some kind of
masculine exercise
but it's totally fake and it's
tyrannical
peter pan syndrome is the precursor to
the tyranny itself so if you take the
peter pan syndrome
which is very common today and mix it
with the anode
then it's very very easy right now to
run at the forefront of any lynch mob
out there
and be this guy runs at the front of the
lynch mob and think you're going to get
laid by the woman
but in reality inside your own mind
you're an 11 year old who has separated
the mind from the body
they're not unified they're not a whole
and that's exactly why you're actually
really
scary and dangerous to other people
mm-hmm
so how has that happened in terms of the
relationship with the mother and father
like from a freudian sense or oh you're
still stuck with the mother you don't
want to go towards the father or i say
you're stuck close to the mamilla this
is the problem with the welfare state
systems we developed marx would have
hated them to be honest about it
the welfare systems basically tax mostly
men
and then redistribute the money and
throw it back to women with children
and then into the hands of the children
so they all become like young diabetics
over
obese and all those kinds of things and
and you know sexually frustrated
insults or whatever but we have so many
massive
psychical problems now with young men
today is because we basically foster
them into being babies
right so this this i in mass
infantilization hits young men even
harder than it hits young women
and and that's exactly what we've done
since 1945
on on you know and it's gone worse over
the last 20 years
and everything from the welfare state to
the complete commodification of all
human relations
to complete commercialization of any
human relationship at all
all of these things and the fact you
stick these guys in pornography in
computer games and they do nothing
that's meaningful to them any longer
means we're going to have huge pandemics
of depression and bipolarity they've
already started
it's going to get worse and worse and
worse here's what beyonce and i and
other guys agree
completely and this is a result caligula
syndrome this is a result of a society
that hates phallus
or completely misunderstands what
phallus is for
it doesn't have the mechanisms to for
for the young men
to to go go away from the you know
doesn't have
an attractive goal for the young men
you know to get off of sucking this
gigantic
you know mother's breasts there is there
is a there is a real
there is a real new there's a lot of
authenticity
to the type of guy that alexander is
describing in the sense
you know the very the very re the very
real question of why
bother why sacrifice is is
is is authentic it's it's it's saying
look
it looks like the society that's set up
around me
is set up in so many ways where any
action i do is going to lead me into a
tragedy
i don't have i don't see that the elder
elves
i don't see elder men who i can respect
and look up to i don't see men who
are you know who got married and had
kids and who look like they're respected
and look like they're doing well i i
i don't see any occupations or jobs
where
it seems like if i work hard i'm going
to be able to do something meaningful
and i'm going to be able to do something
that actually helps people i see people
who are becoming
bureaucrats who aren't helping people i
see people who are
you know uh doing you know like uh david
graber rest in peace david graber
um uh david greater jobs
everything's jobs everything's
empty
you wear you know like you have that uh
you know i forget the movie but it's
like this
yeah how can how can you respect your
father if he's doing a job if
you know if he's not hey
he's not doing something a little bit
heroic or
quality to him what you have to be able
to respect the father what he does how
he handles himself
it's not it's like it's like you know
those horrible parents who say
uh listen to what i say don't watch what
i do no
watch what i do yeah don't even listen
to what i say watch what i do
and and and th this is this is this is
why a lot of men
you know boys and men young men are are
are opting out and i think they're right
to do it and i think that
um uh in that sense there there's going
to be
a huge transition where these these boys
are going to need
a a a a rite of passage and
serious initiation and i think actually
i think actually
the psychedelic revolution might provide
and ceremony
actual deep religious ceremony with
shamans
with people who with with men who have
already gone through their initiation
and have become
men and who have who have overcome their
attachment to the mother and who have
been able to integrate their identity as
a father
and as alexander bard says in the notion
of fatherhood
in the way bard says in terms of
fatherhood is any activity where older
men are taking care of younger men and
trying to point them in the right
direction this is the act of the father
i can be a father to a 20 year old guy
who's
coming to me and looking for guidance
yeah yeah i agree completely yeah that's
exactly what's going on well you almost
want to say amen because it's just
it's so absolutely uh obviously true at
this point
um that that's what we need and it's the
big blind spot of society
on some level yeah and i think it can
only happen with some people first that
go first that's why i talk about
excitology so somebody has to lead by
example
and then other people can mimic that and
they can say okay that worked okay let's
do it
let's see if we can invite more people
two or more guys in that case
to go through that same ritual but this
is what's important here
when you do psych analysis it's
impossible to do it unless you first
learn to think critically about the
world you live in
you first have to understand that for
example if you're going to deal with
peter
pan syndrome or caligula syndrome you
better find out which one you're
actually going to deal with which is
your main problem here
are you refusing to grow up or you
haven't been taught how to grow up or
you don't have self-confidence enough to
grow up and you're stuck at the mammal
although you should have left it when
you were one years old
and now you're 15 years old and you
still haven't left the mamela then
that's peter pan syndrome
needs to be dealt with here's how we
deal with that if your caligula syndrome
you realize that oh my god i live in a
society where
like the pretense that the
normatological has come back and that's
the only alternative forward
and everything is going to return to the
same or otherwise the planet goes down
or some other dystopian idea
and phalluses are hated and men are
wrong and it's called patriarchy and
it's evil or whatever kind of rubbish
you're being told
now if you realize that that's the case
remember that psychoanalysis starts with
learning how to think critically about
yourself and the environment you're
stuck in
that's why a great psych analyst like a
great social analyst
will basically throw you back into the
world where you live so you're forced to
make up your mind about the world within
which you live
you need to learn you need to get
knowledge you need to get informed
once you are in that realm when you when
you you you realize you you get
self-confident from the fact you're
learning
and you're truly understanding i don't
mean critical theory in the sense you're
teaching academia today because it's
usually rubbish
i mean to think critically properly
yeah this is this is this psychoanalysis
great lesson once you've done that you
can then start looking at yourself as
this
empty subject the void that tries to
fill itself with desires and drives and
all those kind of things and
repeats those processes or whatever and
play around with it but you can't do
that unless you first have defined
yourself and what kind of society you
live in
the name for this in our work is
paradigmatics
paradigmatics means you've got to find
out what kind of paradigm you actually
live in
and you will discover very quickly that
most people will tell you live in a
previous paradigm that's already gone
and dead and over so you've got to find
out exactly what kind of world do you
live in now
what kind of environment is this how do
people relate to all the technologies
and things they have around them
and where will people be 30 40 50 years
from now
so you can orientate yourself within
that context i call it the aristotelian
revival we need right now we need to
understand the context where we're at
to understand the different causes of
our behaviors and to do that i think
it's fundamental to first get to a
proper critical theory
so that's the that's the will to
intelligence i think you called it right
no that's social analysis there's also
the will to transcendence well i was
just thinking about the body mind thing
and okay
no no you need to be thick
the world to intelligence is the
separation of
master is a separation of the priest and
the king
within ourselves and certainly within
the community as the two dominant
archetypes to do leaders
the priest is the will to intelligence
the priest
has an urge to accumulate all the
information about history up until now
and provide us with the ah more faulty
that nietzsche talks about so we can
start
fresh then the priest worships and
admires the king or the chieftain
because the king the chieftain
represents the world to transcendence
this is the world to change the world
for the better and to create a new world
a new tomorrow and that starts with
knowing everything about the world you
already operate within
any technologist any engineer will tell
you i need to know everything about
physics and
chemistry and usually also these days
biology to be able to create about the
technologies we're looking for
yes these knowledges are will to
intelligence the urge to accumulate
information
this is why priests in all culture build
libraries store information
save information with the words coming
along in the library or whatever
so information is stored for the future
so you have somewhere to go
to learn that's what the
monasteries used to do that's what
academia pretends to do although it
doesn't do it much very for much longer
but that's exactly what will to
intelligence means
so what we do in our work is that we
split the world to power
in nietzsche just like we then split the
young in taoism
and division between the ora and the
master and this is the world
transcendence and the world to
intelligence the two different things
and here's the take on the machine when
the machine comes along the machine can
only at best do
will to intelligence it can only best
replace the priest in certain functions
but he can never become the king it can
never become the phallus that wants to
change the world for the better
and reach higher and more and make a
more noble world that's impossible the
machine cannot even comprehend that
because that is transcendent that's the
drive towards transcendence in our work
the fourth try yeah that makes sense to
me uh
the the thing i was picking up on was
was um
you know you talked about critical
thinking or being being essential and
that
we're agreed about that but there's also
this this sort of
young men who need to go in on rights of
initiation and and uh you know
in cattle and cattle's book he talks
about death you know then
needing this needing to become aware of
death or become you know face death
on some level uh it means i think a
young
a young man has to face this kind of
violence or face this kind of potential
death and really
become heroic in the face of death or
something that's
just what i was thinking oh yeah but
it's both i mean the rite of passage
is let's do as the fathers did before us
let's have a rite of passage that's well
to transcendence very priestly that's
exactly what psychedelics
it's a psychedelic journey as well right
for example yeah
but then the next thing is here's your
mentor
here's a guy who we as elders believe is
the older version of you
and you can develop your own personality
in the shadow of this guy
under his protection and his fatherly
gaze his phallic gays and his fatherly
love
okay if you do that if you stay within
that realm and you then become the
archetype you're supposed to be so you
can serve the tribe of the community
that's contextual then you have to go
paradigmatic
you have to understand the society
living so we can't just do these sort of
timeless rituals the way we used to do
them to do right of passage and then
automatically you become a father or you
become a mentor or a grown up man
no you also need to understand the
specific times you live in
this is where evertology comes in this
is where will the transcendence concern
this is where the contextual comes in
and that that is why i'm adamant that we
have to develop ceremonies that are
specific for the times we live in
so they make sense today this is why for
example your relationship to the laptop
and the smartphone into the dating apps
and all those things and the computer
games
has to be part of the right of passage
where you renounce certain aspects of
what you did in your behavior
but you enhance others they actually
think oh my god when i do these things i
go constructive i become phallic i
i believe in the vision of the strategy
that i subscribe to i want to be part of
that
and these tools help me do that but
those things are just time pass
waste of time destructive take my time
away
make me child rather than a grown-up man
throw them away
i think that's when the rite of passage
could become really powerful
[Music]
does it make sense to cattle that i'm
working with these two levels or it's
this too almost banal to you
the distinction between will to
intelligence and will to transcendence
yes um makes sense to me
yeah this is what we added we added this
to la khan in digital libido we said
it's not just enough with pure drive and
desire all the fantastic but the
mechanistic drive and the human
desire that comes out of language are
there okay but there's the animalistic
instinct which is of course they're in
lacan too he just doesn't pay much
attention to it
but it helps have instinct in one and
then transcendence in the other and
explore
and understand transcendence as a drive
specifically a phallic drive
it's the drive that is the most
masculine drive of them all is to try
to be part of something bigger than
yourself i just don't know if that's in
contradiction with lacan i know that
what
what um what le khan says about instinct
is that in the human realm
instinct is always drive like instinct
is always in some sense
transcendentalized by the symbolic order
like so for example the example i always
give is like
you know eating um
eating uh sleeping and
homemaking you know okay what we did
exactly what we did was split it we
split it both drives all of those
instincts rather are filtered through
the symbolic order and in some sense
transcendentalized so like
the french the french don't just eat
they
transcendentalize a certain ritual
practice of eating
it's filtered through the symbolic order
or we can never just
we always have to transcendentalize the
drive
yeah okay we just split the drive in two
and kept pure drive as a mechanistic
thing
it's just easy for people to grasp i
think that got better
and then we kept instinct separate as
animalistic so it makes it easier for
people to grasp the two
and then we split the desire between
desire as the desire of desire
and transcendence that's the possibility
of that and the trick we did was kind of
hegelian we did it
we just we just we just imagined that
say you come out of lacan analysis and
you've actually succeeded
in the sense you understand what's
actually going on you're trapped in it
you will be trapped in it you get that
but you can actually understand what's
going on
so you could actually take part in
something that transcends you meaning
for example you you you you can
understand you're gonna die one day but
you can actually leave a heritage that
doesn't have to be absolutely
meaningless it can actually have some
meaning to it
and it helps me at least to understand
that as a drive itself so our drive
system has four drives
instinct air and transcendence and of
course transcendence we usually then
call the divine
or you know it aspires towards the
divine and and you would say that
desire is strictly human it's tied to
language pure drive itself is
mechanistic it's almost like you're a
machine you're just doing it you can't
stop doing it
you're patiently doing it and you can't
stop doing it it just
sticks with you whereas the animalistic
instinct doesn't necessarily have to be
that way
but we just we just made it slightly
more complex maybe more so than we had
to
but i agree la con does not contradict
that it's just that we we developed it
into four drive series
i wonder like me and alexander talk a
lot about about tantra or something
that being an essential um kind of thing
for for
all of this that we're talking about in
a sense uh which is
is a more sophisticated notion of of
sexuality
i wonder if you've reflected on tantra
or if you have any thoughts about tantra
yeah so there's a distinction but that
freud makes between
for pleasure and end pleasure um and of
course the the
the for pleasure is type of like the
enjoyment
i i can't hear you cattle oh we lost
your microphone we lost your microphone
for a second
sorry am i can you hear me yeah yes i'm
kidding yeah
so freud makes a distinction between for
pleasure and end pleasure with four
pleasure being of course
things like foreplay and the end
pleasure being kind of like the build-up
to the orgasm
um and i do think that men today are
um too sloppy with end pleasure
let's say something like that um and
that
uh if tantra is
the sort of an attempt to educate
our sexual drive and to you know prolong
it
and play with it and dramatize it and
and and and
you know play with the for pleasure um
i think that this is an example of a
you know a maturing man okay well i
agree with that but
my my definition of tantra is something
it begins with the sexual metaphor but
it expands into
pretty much everything like it's not
just about sex that would be
but that would be but that would be
endlessly delaying the end pleasure
and expanding the for pleasure so much
that the libidinal energy infuses into
everything and everything in some sense
can become
sexual yeah
or derive in a type of enjoyment which
well bliss everything becomes bliss in
tantra it becomes
bliss basically it becomes sort of bliss
pain too it's not just
sort of a you know a happy birthday yeah
it's exploring a sort of optimization of
living over long periods of time which
is interesting because it's the opposite
of mortito and why not
uh i use tantra in our work because we
introduced the bard absolute and the
bard absolute we think is what's missing
in christianity in islam
and and as certain is missing in western
culture
uh it's it's it's totally alien to an
indian or a chinese person or say
zoroastrian from
persia not everybody absolutely religion
so it is a judaism
the broad absolute essentially that we
don't talk to god directly
talk to the lesser gods even in
catholicism you go and pray to sin
because you can't talk to god himself
and then the saint will talk to god on
your behalf now
that's just this very simple version of
that and so if you think of the temple
of the religion when you're gonna preach
and teach people in the community how
they best
maintain the community number logically
and maybe even aspire to something
better eventologically
you do that you say you're on the stairs
and you're a preacher you preach the
community and that's essentially what
sutra is
surgical knowledge is that this is how
the world operates and if you keep with
the sutra
you can keep with the community and
community keeps going but the time trick
realm is basically to realize that wait
a second though
there is knowledge beyond that but it's
not for everyone
and because not for everyone you got to
be a person either as the talent to be
able to absorb that knowledge or you
come to
gotta come to a certain point in your
life when you've done all the other
things you know you ticked all the boxes
you're supposed to do
and we can now crown you one of the
elders or one of the shamanoids
and you can then go into the tender
ground that's exactly why
we mimic all the way while we're in
sutra but when the mimicking has to stop
yeah you need a crazy wisdom teacher
you're grown up enough
or you're talented enough or you can
handle these situations enough so you
can handle something way beyond that so
you can meet no longer
we can meet god directly in a sense you
know no
it looks like that to the outside world
because yeah exactly
that's how we associate the tantric with
divine realms but actually you become
one of the lesser gods in a way to other
people in the sense that you
are inside a barred absolute and once
you're inside that board up so which is
the opposite of the barred subject and
psychic analysis the bard abs which is
just
basically the bard object in the sense
that you should not go beyond that point
unless you're prepared for it and you're
prepared for it it's not that you choose
to go beyond that point
but but actually somebody says you're
ready for it and you believe them and
they guide you beyond that point well
there's always a part absolute
no matter where yeah and beyond the bard
absolute
uh you find out that the teachers are
crazy western they go absolutely nuts
and behave in the most erratic
erratic ways and you're very ambivalent
about them you know they your wife
and they get drunk and take
tons of drugs away it doesn't matter
they behave like slightly
why because it makes it impossible for
you to mimic them because everything
you've done
up until that point has been mimicking
and the idea with tantra is to
have even if you're still avoid is to
have a sense of self that goes beyond
the strictly mimicking you're no longer
a robot
you become deeply human and that is of
course what shamanoid people
desire because the shamanists are then
hired by everybody else
to talk to the gods on their behalf why
because the shamanoids handle all
communication with external world
the shamanoids are the only people who
can peacefully walk into the next
village without getting killed
the shamanites are the only people who
can walk straight through the
battlefield
with their shamanic dresses on and we
don't kill them because we need them as
go-betweens in case we can finally
arrive at some kind of peace negotiation
in the middle of the war this is what
shamanic people do but because they
handle all external relations between
tribes
they of course also handle the vertical
external relations which are talking to
the gods
this is the origin of the saints the
martyrs and those things in the in the
history of religion
is that these are all shall annoyed
characters but the shamanoid personality
is not for everyone
very few people can handle being
shamanoids staying within a shaman or
state
that is why tantra is not for everyone
in eastern culture that's why we should
not just throw our psychedelics around
into the mouths of anybody opens their
mouth because that will just people
up immensely
we've got to do this carefully we've got
to know what we're doing it's sacred
knowledge
it's done in sacred spaces we have to
behave well chris
is a western way when we do it yeah so
that we cannot be mimicked
so so we've tried sort of mass tantra
before
and it's ended up uh you know in the
1960s by dosing everybody or or
well thankfully oh show cult and things
like that where people just go mad right
but
no but it wasn't even tantra so i'm glad
to say to note that when tantra is being
explored as a commercial product the
capitalist society it's it's so
flat and so boring and so bland and it's
basically just there to sleep with
somebody else but your wife for a while
you know it's just
it's just hippie nonsense it's nothing
to do with tantra in any tibetan or
chinese or indian tradition that i've
ever
known no but that's the name of it and i
think
a western name in the sense of west of
the gobi desert uh
you know looking through islam and
christianity and discovering that
basically mormonism and scientology long
before they existed
um to me that is a strong case for going
into these sort of much more mature
religions that have been around for
thousands of years that have all these
long spiritual traditions
and the deal would follow the matrix
properly and not just throw it away
ready to be commercialized and uh that
is that is the strength of judaism
zoroasterism to me
they're responding to that and vary on a
buddhism certainly is that i'm
in these rich traditions the separation
of tantra sutra
which again is that it's just a where
you stand on the stairs
are you in front of the temple or are
you inside and if you're inside the
temple or in the sacred room
and who's allowed to enter the room only
the people who prepared for it nobody
else should be there
but in that room is where protopianism
will be practiced in the new digital age
that means in that room we isolate
yourself you can practice creativity
on a level we've probably never seen
before in human history that's my great
hope for the man technology interface
that's my singularity and i'll call it
protopianism
the bard absolute that's what we call it
i think it needs to be reinstated and i
think that's part of the maturing of
religion
or what i call the adultification of
western society
we finally come to the point where
civilization itself needs to go through
a rite of passage
and we're not prepared for it all we're
probably more infantile than ever but
it's necessary
we can't solve the current problems we
have ahead of us unless we go through
the adultification process
as a society as a whole
okay so you know we've covered sex
masculinity in god
right the name of kettles yeah i want to
hear a
fantastic book we've talked about all
these subjects like these are the
subjects that have been spontaneously
coming up and it's
all related to sex masculinity in god so
not only is it great it's a great title
it has
and it's all the taboos that that you
know we're struggling against in the
society
um to talk and difficulty we have a
difficult of talking about
these these things i think it's a
wonderful book and
and the book is catalan two friends uh
who basically said
and recorded recorded their dialogue
it's like it's like a great
podcast written it's just it's just and
i think most of all
again as a model which cattle talks a
lot about
it's a great model for inviting a couple
of friends over and do the same
conversation between you
what have you noticed that the trial
agus
is is is something that i don't know i
think the trial august is great somehow
and i think there's a dynamic
presence in a trial log which is not
always present just
in one-on-one uh did you notice that
with with these three guys that you're
working with and or two guys uh let's
say kevin and daniel
kettle well well we we specific i mean
we specifically designed it to to be a
trilog
um and i put a lot of work into
the you know yes uh we live recorded but
um i tried to um
come up with basically uh a structure
for the conversation
and a specific quote for each chapter
which would sort of lead us into a type
of interesting territory that
where you know it wasn't just um
chaotic but we would actually be able to
work towards
some sort of you know new idea or new
perspective on whatever the
the topic of a given chapter was so like
for example
sexual difference or um love and death
or
ethics and morality we really wanted to
go into these uh topics in a in an open
way but a structured way and
we wanted to basically um
you know try to make sense of the
present moment of
love and death the present moment of
ethics and morality the present moment
of sexual difference and
and try to you know give some sort of
you know direction both in method as
bard said other guys can
easily do this and i would encourage
other guys to do this
because it really helps you to sharpen
your own understanding of yourself
um but also to you know
really develop a method like
with the trialog where um people can
collectively
come to new ideas on a higher order
level
um i think it's one of the i think it's
one of the
the great missing pieces of the the
scientific enterprise where you again i
always say
you'll have a textbook on collective
intelligence written by one guy
you know so how well does he know
collective intelligence
i can doesn't sound like he's embodying
it so
i mean this type of thing happens all
the time in science where they'll talk
about distributed intelligence they'll
talk about collective intelligence
they'll talk about self-reflectivity
they'll talk about embodied cognition
but they don't do any of these things
they don't live any of these things
and so we really wanted to live this out
and we wanted to
show that it's possible for three men of
a similar status and a similar age
to come together power share um
disagree but disagree respectfully in a
way that the conflict produces new ideas
yeah i agree completely so it's path as
a world to transcendence so the way i
look at it is this if you just got to
summarize it pedagogically to 23 year
old who might want to read sex and
masculinity god
i would say this instead of looking for
recognition from women
you should find recognition from other
men this is how three guys sat down
wrote a trial and got the recognition
they needed from other men
that's what recognition is for a man
because a woman is somebody you deliver
to is that somebody you seek recognition
from
and that colors the entire book so i
would say i would say that's a strong
advice for the
book and get inspired to do similar
things if you're 23 years old
and by the way for next year 2021
hopefully the coronal be over by
then i would love to do men's work
together
with the two of you i mean uh the
european men's gathering and the
men's movement across europe at the
moment inspires me immensely
this book that you wrote cattle with
your friends as part of that process and
uh andrew and i've been involved for a
couple years and i i really look forward
to develop new
new forms of men's work together with
you guys i think it would be absolutely
awesome and and
because we're basing it on the oda
master
the mind work and the bodywork half of
each at least every event you
work on your mind and your body yeah you
know and it starts
without just a new age event there's
there's no no no it's not
that's just a touchy feely thing but it
also is brilliant bodied and really
alive and really
kind of dynamic and yeah yeah
it's really built from what men discover
when they're together with other men and
ask themselves the serious sincere
question
what do we need what do we need as a
group what do we need individually
that's the question we're answering at
these events and just like your book did
uh and i really look forward to working
with you guys next year and hopefully
once the corona is over and the face
masks are gone we can start doing these
major men's events again
because i'd love them to be physical i
hate to do this this stuff digital this
should definitely be physical in the
body
with the bodies present absolutely we
massively miss something with the
virtual i mean it has to be it has to be
physical we have to be
there wrestling with each other in the
real yeah absolutely
yeah yeah wrestling
in the mud can be metaphorical or
literal like
i mean i see like what we're doing right
now as a type of wrestling match and
it's uh it's what it's it's what what i
think good men
can do is to um you know in you know pl
play play in competition and um
and to really sharpen each other not in
a way that i win and you lose or you win
and i lose
but in a way that we all sharpen each
other and this is
kind of how we started the conversation
with i'm talking about the
atomistic culture and and moving into
the spirit of collaboration right yeah
it's protopianism that's the word for it
and and
it's participatory culture take it in
the next step besides the men's movement
for example personally
me my team are involved with burners and
burning man and the
more than 200 spin-offs from burning man
around the world that even more interest
in the burning man today
and now after i came back from prague i
love the hackers out there i love the
open source movements and things like
that and
they do decentralize the internet to
fight the tech giants i
i became best friends with douglas
rushkova that's just wonderful in itself
those three things to me the burner
movement and the hackers and the men's
movement and the new women's movement
that comes out of it the sort of new
post-feminist women's movement too these
are really great things that are
happening
at the moment and they were they got
more energy out of digital during the
current amounts but we're all
dying for the physical events now and
for the augmented reality of being both
digital and physical at the same time
i'm dying for physical events and yeah
i'm gonna go to tuscany for a while now
write a book and and isolate myself with
a face mask
when i walk outside the door but i'm so
much dying to get beyond this so we can
go back to the physical meetups
yes yeah indeed meanwhile we write books
and we make podcasts
yeah all three of us